<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief treatise containing a full discovery 1. Of Cæsars politique state, or civill government, 2. Of the divine politique state, or kingdome of Christ Jesus, given him of his father. 3. Of the devilish politique state or kingdome of Antichrist. Laid open in the essentiall and main circumstantiall parts of each body or state by substantiall and fundamentall reasons and principles of policy both divine and humane, and confirmed by holy Scripture. Whereby the great and intolerable grievances of Christ Jesus and his subjects are made knowne: also how honourable magistracy and civill government is, and how farre it extends, without intrenching upon the prerogative of Christ, doth evidently appear in this treatise. Humbley presented to the serious consideration of the Kings most excellent Majesty, and the high court of Parliament now assembled. By Michael Quintine.</title>
            <author>Quintyne, Michael.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Q227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E163_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R649</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873001</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873001</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156944</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91609)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156944)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 29:E163[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief treatise containing a full discovery 1. Of Cæsars politique state, or civill government, 2. Of the divine politique state, or kingdome of Christ Jesus, given him of his father. 3. Of the devilish politique state or kingdome of Antichrist. Laid open in the essentiall and main circumstantiall parts of each body or state by substantiall and fundamentall reasons and principles of policy both divine and humane, and confirmed by holy Scripture. Whereby the great and intolerable grievances of Christ Jesus and his subjects are made knowne: also how honourable magistracy and civill government is, and how farre it extends, without intrenching upon the prerogative of Christ, doth evidently appear in this treatise. Humbley presented to the serious consideration of the Kings most excellent Majesty, and the high court of Parliament now assembled. By Michael Quintine.</title>
                  <author>Quintyne, Michael.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed. 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156944:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156944:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A BRIEF TREATISE containing a full DISCOVERY</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of <hi>Caeſars</hi> politique ſtate, or civill Government,</item>
               <item>2. Of the Divine politique ſtate, or Kingdome of Chriſt Jeſus, given him of his Father.</item>
               <item>3. Of the deviliſh politique ſtate or kingdome of Antichriſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Laid open in the eſſentiall and main circumſtantiall parts of each body or ſtate by ſubſtantiall and fundamentall reaſons and principles of policy both divine and humane, and confirmed by holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>Whereby the great and intolerable grievances of Chriſt Jeſus and his ſubjects are made knowne:</p>
            <p>Alſo how honourable Magiſtracy and civill Government is, and how farre it extends, without intrenching upon the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of Chriſt, doth evidently appear in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>Humbly preſented to the ſerious conſideration of the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, and the High Court of Parliament now aſſembled.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Michael Quintine.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 22.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Render therefore to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and unto God the things that are Gods.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 <hi>Theſſ. 2.8, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And then ſhall that wicked one be revealed, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the ſpirit of his mouth, and ſhall destroy with the brightneſſe of his comming.</p>
            </q>
            <p>London printed. 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:156944:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156944:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HIGH COVRT OF Parliament, the Right Honourable the Lords and Barons, and the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS, to all and every of them now aſſembled, be a full bleſſing of wiſdom and right ſpirit, from the glorious Trinity, ſutable to their callings, and the weighty occaſions that concerne them therein.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to my undoubted duty in diſcharging my Conſcience of fulfilling the will of Ieſus Chriſt, I doe preſent to both Houſes of this Honourable Court, the greateſt and moſt generall cauſe of the particular grievances of Chriſt Ieſus, and his ſervants, the upright, the innocent, and tender in conſcience; which as it did in ſpeciall manner concerne my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Lord the King, from whoſe hand it might moſt ſeaſonably have been caſt
<pb facs="tcp:156944:3"/>upon the conſideration of this high Court, from whence onely do iſſue all politicke acts, ſtatute-lawes, and ordinances, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters Eccleſiaſticall and Civill within his Majeſties Realme of England, I procured to be preſented to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe owne hand in Ianuary laſt, 1640. The copy of the paſſages therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined; leſt thoſe ſhould ſleep, I have here again recited, and do preſent them unto you: accept &amp; peruſe them as you ſee cauſe.</p>
            <p>And this be pleaſed to take notice of; as the Lawes of Divine and Civill Policie admit not of two heads in one body, ſo likewiſe doth not the tranſcendent and glorious Kingdome of Chriſt, which is above the humane element, admit of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Lawmakers in confining conſcience and diſpoſing of matters thereto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the ſame Scripture and reaſon which denieth <hi>Caeſar</hi> to ſit on Chriſts throne; denieth you power of making Lawes for the ordering the Lawes thereof, who ſhall increaſe or diminiſh the liberties, Lawes, and privileges of the Goſpel of Chriſts Kingdom, but they muſt incurre the curſe,
<pb facs="tcp:156944:3"/>and who ſhall be wiſer than his maker but to his owne deſtruction?</p>
            <p>The cauſe aforeſaid of all grievances of Chriſt and his ſervants is oppreſsion of conſcience, otherwiſe conſcionable op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion, for ſo it is taken, although it be impoſsible, being oppreſsion, ſo to be; the root from whence it ſpringeth, the tree, and every part of it, is diſcovered by the following paſſages, to which I referre you.</p>
            <p>And that you may not be found falſe in the truſt committed to you by the King and Countrey, for the ordering of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of this Land, for the peace and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the Church of God, and likewiſe of the King and Common-wealth; let it be your ſpeciall care to remove and repeal all things and ſtatutes, tending to the bondage of conſcience, be not wiſer than the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in continuing and eſtabliſhing penall acts, and ſtatutes, to bring people under conformity, in externall worſhip; if you conſider from whence every good and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gift is, who it is that giveth light, what it is that is acceptable to him, to whom all worſhip is due, and that Law,
<pb facs="tcp:156944:4"/>Do unto all as you would they ſhould do unto you: yee cannot, neither would ye go about Antichriſtian-like, to make yokes for conſcience, it is moſt Papiſticall, and why will ye do what yee condemne your ſelves in others? do not correct Tyrants with tyranny, but overcome evill with good: if you fear Papiſts wil be treacherous to State &amp; Common-wealth, let them have a civill providence over them for preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in caſe they or any of them prove ſo, as ſome prove naught and treacherous of all Religions, let them have civill cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reclion; for it is that, not conſcience keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth people in generall within bounds of Civility, and leave the cutting off, or rooting out of errours in matters ſpirituall to the free uſe of the ſword of Gods Spirit, which is ſharper than a two-edged ſword; and fear yee not but in caſe of liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, true Religion, which onely is of God, will have the upper hand, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt approbation of all civilly diſpoſed perſons; if it be not <hi>Caeſars</hi> due, to ſit on the Eccleſiaſticall Throne, nor any mans beſide, look you to it, how you ſet or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb facs="tcp:156944:4"/>any perſon thereon; and except God had conſecrated and ſet apart a parcell of the earthly revenues for ſpirituall uſes, how dare ye powers of the earth to do it, or to allow of it? but to avoid tediouſneſſe, I commend you to the ſerious minding of the following paſſages, hoping you will not ſlight what is ſubſtantially appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to your ſelves, by the injunction of the will of the Lord Almighty, leſt yee be found reſiſters of God: and ſo I remain yours in all due ſervice, even to my power and life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Michael Quintyne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:156944:5"/>
            <head>To the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas your moſt ſubmiſsive and faithfull ſubject hath in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure perceived, and in the following Treatiſe ſubſtantially diſcovered the way of greateſt deceit, wherein God and the King are inſufferably and moſt ſubtilly deprived of their due, and doth in the freedome and ſtrength of fidelity in the ſight of all hazards of good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, humbly preſent it unto your most Excellent Majeſtie.</p>
            <p>His juſt and humble requeſt is, that your Highneſſe will be gratiouſly pleaſed to accept of it accordingly, and now the Scales of this your Kingdome are in uſe, let it be truly weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not caſt by, and as it is found in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, for the main ſcope and ſubſtance thereof, even ſo, let it be done to your poor ſubject, who during life, ſhall heartily pray for your long happy and moſt proſperous reigne,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Michael Quintyne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156944:5"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS moſt Excellent Majeſty, Gods greateſt and moſt ſpeciall Officer and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter within his Majeſties Dominions in place of Authority and power of Juſtice, be a full bleſſing from the bleſſed Trinity, of a right and ſuteable ſpirit, for his high Calling, with all truly deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able iſſues thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the cauſe of Heavens right no man is injoyned ſilence, but may move the caſe before the greateſt of men on earth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.31, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. who are but men in perſon, though Gods anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Gods in place of Government, to whom with God belongeth a due to be rendered, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7 Let not place of honour, as it hath been in times paſt, be an occaſion of pride, and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, whereby men have forgotten that they were men, and the remembrance of their Maſter, his cauſe, and ſervants, the upright and innocent; but exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, conſider, and ſcorne not, the reall demonſtration and reaſonable motion in the caſe of greateſt wrong put upon the Trinity and the whole Hoſt of Heaven, and your Majeſties dignity and honour of civill Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156944:6"/>for reliefe wherein if you do not your part, let your neglect reſt with your ſelfe, for I will preſent it to you with my life in my hand, accept it as you pleaſe.</p>
            <p>The Kingdome of the Goſpel, the divine politique ſtate, the Eccleſiaſticall Government, or viſible Church, which was given to Chriſt Jeſus by his Father, is by the Kingdom of Darkneſſe the falſe Eccleſiaſticall ſtate, and falſe Church, together with the deluded and abuſed aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of your own civil ſtate, the honorable Ordinance of God, utterly defaced, trodden under foot, excluded and baniſhed your Dominions, to the greateſt diſhonour, and undervaluing of the Trinity, the power, wiſdom, and goodneſſe thereof, repreſented and expreſſed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance and eſtabliſhment of the ſaid Kingdome of Chriſt, to the greateſt deſtruction, deſolation, diſconſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and loſſe of conſcionable and ſaintlike perſons, and to the great overthrow of your owne ſubjects, and decay or ſtrength in your owne Dominions.</p>
            <p>To prove the truth of this cauſe is not hard, the Lawes and Rules of the policy of Divinity and Humanity jumpe home to it: neither will the Lawes and Rules of deviliſh policy, be able to contrary it, although they may dazzle and cloud it.</p>
            <p>All bodies of policy, as well Eccleſiaſticall as Civil, true and falſe, as all other things, do conſiſt of matter and forme, by the quality of which two eſſentiall parts all politique bodies tranſcendent, different, and contrary in nature, are reaſonably and ſubſtantially diſtinguiſhed, and knowne one from the other : and all bodies poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique of one nature, whether Eccleſiaſticall, true, falſe, or civill are diſtinguiſhed one from another by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, limitation, and confines of thoſe two forenamed eſſentiall parts.</p>
            <p>The realty and truth of this Rule will appear in the incontradictable and undeniable diſcovery and manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156944:6"/>of each politique body and Kingdom in an eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall way.</p>
            <p>Every body and ſtate of policy conſiſteth of like, or one and the ſame eſſentiall and circumſtantiall parts in reſpect of name and number, the difference or means of diſtinction lieth in the tranſcendent, different, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary qualities of thoſe parts.</p>
            <p>Circumſtantiall differences are of conſequence, the miſplacing, miſapplying, and miſuſing of any ſuch part in any body of policy, deſerveth reproof and diſclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the members or ſubjects of any ſuch body; but eſſentiall differences miſplacing, miſapplying, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing any ſuch parts is intolerable and incommunicable, and requireth ſeparation: the truth of all theſe things will be moſt fully proved by humane and naturall reaſon, and holy Scripture, is ſetting forth the ſeverall kindes of bodies of policy in their eſſentiall and main circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall parts.</p>
            <p>That there is a true and falſe Eccleſiaſticall ſtate, I need not ſtand to prove, but refer it to the ſeverall defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions and full demonſtration of them juſtifiable from Scripture, Lawes of all policy, and common experience, for all <hi>Europe</hi> granteth the ſame, and moſt forreigne and domeſtique wars and jars are more concerning Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall affairs, than all the matters in the earth beſides, according as Chriſt prophetically ſpeaketh, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 5, 6, 7. The whole earth is filled with the cry, <hi>Lo here, Lo there,</hi> the voice of greateſt deceivers, of which ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care is to be had for the avoiding them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28.</p>
            <p>And that the world in generall, and moſt eſpecially, my native King and his Dominions, may not continue in contention, which is the readieſt way to confuſion, and to be made a prey to ſtrangers about which is the true Church, or about circumſtances thereof, I have with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156944:7"/>heart in hand, yea heart in hand, undertaken, and ſhall eſſentially and fully make it appear from the Rule of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and humane wiſdom and policy, that it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for any nationall Church to be the true Church of Chriſt, or to be righted by force of Armes, in caſe it were really ſo; either by the King in way of offence, or by his ſubjects in way or defence; and why ſhould not great ones be as ready to try and prove the truth hereof, as to kill me in wrath, which no way accompliſheth Gods will in righteouſneſſe, <hi>Iam</hi> 1.20. But what Effects ſhall be expected of Creatures lifted up above their Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but actions of pride and ſcorne, in oblivion of God and man, and what Lawes of Divinity ſhall rule the Potentates of the Earth, who make Lawes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines for the ſame: the glory of high powers is mercy and the grace of humanity is to be humble and faultleſſe, not cowardly and murderous; and that I may briefly come at, and accompliſh the performance of what I have undertaken, even eſſentially to diſcover the Church of Chriſt, to be trodden under foot, and made deſolate, by on Antichriſtian and falſe Eccleſiaſticall ſtate, through the aſſiſtance of the civill ſtate, obteined by deluſion, and deceivableneſſe of unrighreouſneſſe, in all the Kingdoms of the Earth; I have thought it neceſſary to begin with a diſcovery of the Civil State, in the eſſentiall parts of it, the circumſtantiall ones alſo, and the uſe of the whole.</p>
            <p>Civill State or body of humanity, whereſoever thou dwelleſt in any meaſure of truth and realty, thou art Gods Ordinance, the off-ſpring of the ſecond Table of the Morall Law of God, the Image of Innocency in the firſt Creation, in man towards man thou art the Parent of all Nations, in whole honour and diſhonour is length and ſhortneſſe of dayes.</p>
            <p>The ſubject or material part of the conſiſtance of this body of Civility is Mankindle in generall, conteined
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156944:7"/>within the limits and confines of any ſuch body.</p>
            <p>The formall or part of life which giveth being to this Civil politique body, is the Kingly or Regal Civil poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Power, by which any member hath any politique motion, actively or paſſively, by which alſo any Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereto hath any vigour or current.</p>
            <p>The quality of both theſe eſſentiall parts is meerly civill and humane, and ſuch as have relation to this ſtate, concerneth them onely in temporall affairs, for the civill ordering and governing their perſons and eſtates accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law of equity between man and man.</p>
            <p>To prove the matter and forme of this, Civil body po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, to be as aforeſaid, the reaſon of all unions and bodies in the world ſerveth (hand pat) to do it, for the matter and forme of every body is comprehended with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelfe, neither without either of thoſe two parts can the body well or ill ſubiſt; the Creatour, Parent, and Inſtitutour can be no part of the Creature, production and platforme or inſtitution, and all other things, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this body are circumſtantiall, and ſerve properly to prove the quality of the eſſential parts to be meerly civil and humane.</p>
            <p>The inſtrumentall meanes of the being of this body is ordinarily Victory or Conqueſt, by force of Armes, whereof onely mens bodies and goods are capable, for conſcience who is all the witneſſes of a reaſonable, or unreaſonable ſoul is free, beyond the reach of the power of man to command and ſubdue, becauſe if a man ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject his body unto the ſword of the Magiſtrate to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the freedom and peculiar uſe of his conſcience, and ſoul, as in ſome caſes Chriſt adviſeth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.17, 18. Alſo <hi>verſe</hi> 28 <hi>&amp;</hi> 39 and looſeth the uſe of his body and bodily life, his conſcience and ſoul is not overcome and ſubdued, but overcommeth, which plainly proveth the quality and diſpoſition of this body to be humane.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:156944:8"/>
The manner of the being of this body, ſtate, or plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, which was and may be when that of Chriſt was not and may not be, it is of imparity, ſuperiority and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Authority, conſiſting of lordly and inferiour of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; which are neceſſary for the well being thereof; for what elſe ſhould rule nationall and confuſed lumps of the curſed poſterity of <hi>Adam,</hi> and it is but meet that ſome in order of office ſhould have a ſword ready drawn to cut off intolerably uncivil, and inhumane perſons; and to diſable them in their ſtrength and command of eſtate; and that all uncivill and brutiſh perſons and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be prevented, which is the onely meanes of a peaceable and godly life; all Chriſtians are exhorted to pray for all men in Civil Government, for Kings and all in place of Authority, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. And this alſo is a meanes to diſtinguiſh and diſcerne the quality of the eſſence of this body to be as aforeſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.24, 25, 26, 27.</p>
            <p>The Lawes, Statutes, and Ordinances belonging to this body communicable between the head and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, and conveighed from one to another by the ſeverall offices of the ſtate thereof; they all generally<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tend to the prevention of oppreſſion, and preſervation of equity in the civil uſe of mens bodies and perſonall eſtates, the truth hereof daily experience teſtifieth in the uſe of all Courts of common juſtice and belonging to the Laity, this witneſſeth the Spirit of Chriſt who ſuffered under Civill Authority approving their ſtately calling and the Lawes and Ordinances, and the good and neceſſary uſe of them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. This likewiſe proveth the quality of the eſſentiall parts of this body to be hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and civil onely.</p>
            <p>Divine politique body, true Eccleſiaſticall ſtate, viſible Church of Chriſt, or Kingdome, to which belongs the Goſpel and all the Records of new Teſtament; thou art
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156944:8"/>the new Jeruſalem, the Body comprehending the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of all Types and ſhadowes, the perfection of all order of ſacrifice, the union of the fulneſſe of him that filleth all things, thou art the Government of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Prince the Son of <hi>David,</hi> of which there ſhall be no end, <hi>Iſay</hi> 9.6, 7. This is the moſt beautifull daughter of the firſt Table of the Moral Law, the moſt perfect and fulleſt reſemblance of the invisible bond in divine nature, the compleateſt uſe whereof the elect ſhall enjoy, when they have put off their mortality, and are all accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when alſo Chriſt alſo ſhall deliver up his Kingdome, and government to his Father, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which reſemblance and expreſſion of the Law written in the heart ſhall remain for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>The ſubject or material part of this divine politique bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and true Eccleſiaſticall ſtate, (of the true Son and Heire apparent of God, and right Succeſſour of the Crowne and Eccleſiaſticall Throne of <hi>David,</hi> the Alone Redeemer of the whole company of Gods elect, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> both Jewes and Gentiles, who brake downe the partition-wall, the Jewiſh nationall ſtate, and ſet up and eſtabliſhed a divine ſpirituall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, capable of the Saints, of all ſorts whatſoever) Is the ſort of all mankinde which Jeſus Chriſt pronounceth bleſſed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. Such as worſhip God in ſpirit and in truth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.23, 24. without reſpect to Nation or Tribe, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34, 35. In ſhort it is faithfull perſons, beleevers, reall, ſaintlike people, as the ſeverall Epiſtles to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches nominated in the New Teſtament do declare; to ſhut up the proof of this truth that the ſubject or mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall part of the Kingdome of Chriſt is as aforeſaid, of Chriſtian people take alſo this one witneſſe more, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.8, 9 Here take notice, reall profeſſion giveth reall being to members, and is the forme of a member, but not the forme of the Church, but the material quality thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:156944:9"/>
But the formall part of this divine politique body or true Eccleſiaſticall ſtate or kingdom which Chriſt Jeſus hath upon earth, which alſo is the life of the ſame, is the divine regall and kingly politique power of Chriſt; by which every member performeth every Church action, whereby every Law in every Office is communicable, and executed; in this ſenſe, not in a perſonall ſenſe ſpeaketh Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p>The quality of the two eſſentiall parts of this divine politique body is divine love, the Fountain of all merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full goodneſſe, from whence iſſueth every good gift to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, and the communicable benefits thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and man; this is the quality of wiſdoms houſe, derived from the Father and the Son, and expreſt by the holy Spirit proceeding from both, and lively ſet forth in the matter and forme of the ſame, as largely will appear by the diſcovery of the circumſtantiall parts, belonging to the being and welbeing of this body.</p>
            <p>The inſtrumentall meanes of the being of this divine politique body or union, is by agreement and free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of love, iſſuing from one Lord through one Faith, one Spirit, one Baptiſme, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.12, 13 There is no other inſtrumentall meanes of a peculiar body, conſiſtting of Volunteers; and of ſuch conſiſteth this Kingdome of the Lambe of God, as prophetically ſpeaketh the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt by way of proclamation, <hi>Iſai</hi> 55.1. Fulfilling the ſame in like manner, ſpeaketh the ſame Spirit, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. In this way a right Captain accompliſheth a right Band or body of Souldiers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.14. By inſtinct of nature, not compulſion, Birds of a Feather flocke together, this main circumſtantiall part belonging to the being of this body aforeſaid, declareth it to be the Tabernacle of God, who is love, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.16. which is the prepared dwelling for perſons of love, <hi>Revel</hi> 21.1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:156944:9"/>
The ſtate platforme or manner of being of this Kingdom of heaven upon earth, wherein the matter and forme are united, and the divine Lawes and Ordinances there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of executed, and performed, conſiſteth of Offices of ſervice, not of command and authority, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.25, 26, 27. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.24, 25, 26, 27. And is the perfect Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme or repreſentation of the moſt compleat current of divine, and moſt perfect love, as the onely neceſſary Offices cf Adminiſtration of the head, which in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity as in humanity are three; to wit, direction, proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and protection; and becauſe humanity is inſeparable from Chriſtianity, wiſdom hath left civil protection to the head thereof, but hath provided an Office of diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution for his ſubjects, in neceſſity, and tender atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance for the ſicke and weake in body, that his body may be as one in all things, communicating according to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion the gifts and graces which God hath given them, for the building up and for divine and reaſonable preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of one another, and this the holy Ghoſt teſtifieth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4, 5, 6, 7, 8. This alſo maketh it plain that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the diſpoſing of Offices and execution of all Lawes and Ordinances truly Eccleſiaſticall and belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this body of Chriſt which is the Church, <hi>Col</hi> 1.24. is in the Church, and derived from the Church, as plainly witneſſeth, <hi>Matth</hi> 18.17. here is the ſtate or manner of being of the houſe of God, which is the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. of the body of parity, whoſe members are all Kings and Prieſts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. This is the ſtate of the body (not the body of the ſtate,) which is the repreſentation or expreſſion of the current of the divine nature of the Church of Chriſt which is the expreſſe Image of the forme thereof, and when that faileth, members or Church ceaſe to be, and ſtate &amp; all; for this ſee the ſeven Churches mentioned in <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>cl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This circumſtantiall part belonging to the being of this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156944:10"/>body, declareth the matter and forme to be qualified as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The Lawes, Statutes, and Ordinances belonging to this body of Chriſt are tranſcending in nature thoſe of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity (which prevent oppreſſion and enjoyne equity and civil and reaſonable uſe of mens perſons and eſtates:) for theſe not onely allow the ſame; but prevent oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, injoyne equity, and command mercy and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yea, doing good for evil, in all caſes belonging to ſoul and body, thus Chriſt teacheth Chriſtians, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.44, 45, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus the Spirit of Chriſt is exerciſed, and againſt ſuch there is no Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.22, 23. In the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of ſuch is fulfilling the Law of Love, eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Son of God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.34. Theſe divine, yea, moſt heavenly Lawes, &amp;c. manifeſtly diſcovereth the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and forme of the body of Chriſt his Viſible Church, to be qualified as aforeſaid, to the bodies of ſuch a conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did the Apoſtles write their Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>Deviliſh politique body, falſe Eccleſiaſticall ſtate, Viſible Church of Antichriſt, or Kingdome to which belongeth the Charter bookes of humane Conſtitutions, and Canons, and all Records of Heatheniſh and Jewiſh nationall Traditions, touching matters Eccleſiaſticall, and caſes of Conſcience; Thou art the man of ſin, whoſe compleat image conſiſteth eſpecially in the breach of the firſt Table of the Morall Law, the fulleſt expreſſion whereof is in taking Gods power from him, and Chriſt his kingly Office from him, ſitting in the Temple of God which is Conſcience, (for God dwelleth not in Temples made with hands) as God, and exalting thy ſelfe above all that is called God, commanding the Conſcience of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde in the way of politique (which onely and property is publique) worſhip, for in no other ſenſe can any ſit in the Temple of God, or exalt himſelfe above all that is called God; Thou art <hi>Babylon</hi> the great, the myſtery of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156944:10"/>iniquity, who robbeſt God of his honour, in uſurping the Prerogative Royall of his Son, for thou interpoſeſt with thy power Eccleſiaſticall, which ſnareth and captivateth all Nations, in the liberties of their conſciences, perſons, perſonall and temporall eſtates; thou art the City ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Egypt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for no filthy perſon liveth that liveth not in thee, and the height of thy power <hi>Egypt</hi> like oppoſeth God, for who ſhall get out of thy merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and more than inhumane murderous clutches? thou committeſt ſin by a Law, and putteſt a man to death for conſcience ſake, thou art the devils maſter-peece, the expreſſe image of deviliſh inhumanity, <hi>Cain</hi> like ſpoiling the innocent, and what thou canſt not reſtore, the earth cannot bear a fuller meaſure or pride, craft, and envie, than thou art compoſed of, (the unlimited compoſition whereof is the devil himſelfe) thou art a body of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, an hotch-potch without reſpect of good or bad, rich or poor, bond or free, devilliſh, humane or divine.</p>
            <p>The ſubject or materiall part of this falſe Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body or Kingdom of Antichriſt, is mankinde in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, without any reſpect of ſpiritual quality, or Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſpirit and divine diſpoſition, onely with relation to an enforced and conjured profeſſion of Chriſt, which is of the devils putting on, not Chriſts, and being compelled it is the garment of Hypocriſie, not of uprightneſſe, and in the fleeſt uſe is often made an Hypocrites cloak, which is the very oppoſite quality of the material part of Chriſts Church, but the ſpeciall and choſen diſpoſition of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, which is juſtified by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.5. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. 2 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7, 8. alſo <hi>verſes</hi> 16, 17.</p>
            <p>The formall part which is the politique power of the falſe Eccleſiaſticall ſtate or body of deviliſh policy, is dragoniſh, violent and compulſive commanding powers of death, to ſeazon ſuch as will not ſubject their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156944:11"/>to it; or rather be ſlavonized therein; which is clean contrary to heavenly powers, and is a ſtarke enemy to humanity both perſonall and politique, for there is none under heaven able to give light or peace, or to deal for anothers conſcience between God and him, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary conceit whereof, begotten by deluſion and conceived by corruption of humane nature, hath and will produce more unnaturall and unreaſonable wars and plagues upon the earth than it can bear with a ſeeming to ſubſiſt; that the quality of the formall part of the falſe Eccleſiaſticall body is really ſuch as is now propoſed, take theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for witneſſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. and <hi>verſe</hi> 7, 8. alſo <hi>verſe</hi> 15, 16, 17. This is the expreſſe image of the devil ruling in the generation of <hi>Cain</hi> and curſed ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> to their utter ruine, if it be not looked into in time.</p>
            <p>The inſtrumentall meanes of the being of this body (with the other main circumſtantiall parts) prove the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the forenamed eſſentiall parts to be as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>For it is produced and effected by a compulſive power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full proclamation, conjured out of the civil powers of the earth by lying wonders and deluſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.5, 6, 7. alſo <hi>verſe</hi> 24. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.13, 14.</p>
            <p>The ſtate or manner of being of this body of deviliſh policy, or which is falſely called Eccleſiaſticall, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, it is moſt magnificently majeſticall and tyrannicall, full of offices of greateſt ſuperiority and higheſt authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. and are more for gain than adminiſtration of any good, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. This circumſtantiall part teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the matter and forme to be as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The Lawes, Statutes, and Ordinances, Conſtitutions, and Canons, of this body of Antichriſt, are deviliſh and inhumane, oppoſite to thoſe of the body of Chriſt, and moſt pernicious to humanity; theſe binde Conſcience which Chriſts Lawes ſet free, and compell externall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in circumſtantiall matters, which breedeth more
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156944:11"/>hypocriſie than ſincerity, and deſtroyeth civilly diſpoſed perſons, for the proper and peculiar uſe of their owne Conſciences, the truth hereof, witneſſeth all perſons which have ſuffered, do and ſhall ſuffer for their Conſciences; theſe are compulſive and enforcing Conſcience, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſet on foot with fair pretences, yet are ſuch ſnares and traps for men, that thereby their Conſciences are made very ſlaves, or their perſons and perſonall eſtates ruined; of theſe the Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> ſpeaketh pertinently in way of caution and preadmonition, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8. alſo <hi>verſe</hi> 20, 21, 22, 23. Theſe circumſtantiall things alſo belonging to the being of this body, declare the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the matter and forme to be moſt palpably, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Moſt noble King, impartially let former paſſages be conſidered, and call to minde of what generation you came, of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in Paradiſe, and in the time of their innocency were miſcarried by temptation of the devil; what may be the condition of their poſterity, ſince the curſe paſſed upon them and their being thruſt out of the Preſence Garden of God by head and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; though I conceive your calling to be the chiefeſt that is given to the ſons of men, and although God hath given you a Land flowing with milke and honey, yet I am perſwaded you are no more privileged from tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and tranſgreſſion, againſt God, than were your firſt parents, and thoſe Kings of Iſrael (which were Types of Chriſt the King of new Jeruſalem) whoſe calling or ſtate and ſeat was above yours, yet no diſparagement to yours neither, for upon that Throne ſitteth the Son of God, and Lord of <hi>David;</hi> if your firſt parents were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by flattery and an ambitious inclination, and if they by looking after more than God gave them loſt what they had, may not their poſterity be taken in the ſame ſnare; yea, they are ſubjected to it under a curſe, which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156944:12"/>followed ſince their fall; if the true Light which lighteth every man that commeth into the World, was in the World, and the World was made by him, and the World knew Him not; if He came unto his owne, and his owne received Him not, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1 9, 10, 11. may we not ſuſpect our owne averſneſſe and the double advantage our old falſe friend the devil, who is worſe than an open enemy to all mankinde, hath againſt us, take notice of the paſſages of Scripture before mentioned, and theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.43. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.24. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.18. If there be a generation to whom nothing is pure, but even their minde and conſcience is defiled, which profeſſe they know God, but in workes denie him, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.15, 16. who will talke of Chriſt or teach Him, yet deny Him to be come in the fleſh, I mean ſo as to yeeld him the Throne of his father <hi>David,</hi> to ſit as King in matters Eccleſiaſticall, and to let him rule in the Element of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is that ſpirit of Antichriſt, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.3. O noble King, is not a double jealouſie of being deceived neceſſarily called upon in you, whom theſe forenamed perſons have made ſupreme Head of the Church, as if one body could have two heads, or two bodies (different in nature) one head, of which interpoſition and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the Lawes of your owne policy admit not; be judge your ſelfe, it is not outward religious performances pleaſe God, witneſſe <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Abe:</hi> under pretence of long prayers ſome devour widowes houſes: what is accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with God of this nature, ſee <hi>Iames</hi> 1.26, 27. To be ſhort, fully plain and faithfull, do but conſider the Book or <hi>Revelation,</hi> which from the fifth Chapter includeth the diſcovery of the ſtate of Chriſt and his Church, and Antichriſt and his Kingdom, and the birth, life and death of him, and the main particular paſſages of the combate, between them both, and behaviour of the Kings of the earth therein toward either ſide, and obſerve how poor
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156944:12"/>deluded man, in the ſtate and ſeat of Kings is beſet, when the vials of Gods wrath are poured out to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Beaſt, eſpecially when he is touched upon his ſeat and revenue, which is his life and livelihood, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.13, 14. Moſt royall Soveraigne, be not angry and full of wrath which accompliſheth not the will of God, <hi>Iames</hi> 1.20. But look well to your going, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.15, 16.</p>
            <p>And be pleaſed now to take into your hand the line of truth which defineth all the Creatures and things upon the face of the earth whatſoever, and judge and deal by all ſtates and bodies of policy according to their ſeverall natures and qualities of their eſſentiall parts, and of their circumſtantiall parts, which belong unto them; wherein the Rules of holy Scripture and of humane reaſon and policy, will bear you out againſt all oppoſition.</p>
            <p>View the Eccleſiaſticall ſtates within your owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, which are ſo apt to breed wars, to maintain the truth of their being, and to call for ſubſcription thereof from all others, and examine how the quality of their eſſentiall and circumſtantiall parts ſuit with that of Chriſts Church, or with that of Antichriſt, and accordingly you may account of them, and deal by them, ſo farre as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth you in your ſtate of civility. And thus farre I can do no leſſe than move your Majeſty to do, ſithence to God and <hi>Caeſar</hi> belongeth a due; and that you would take to what is your owne, and give unto God the things that are Gods, to which Act I am confident all good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subjects would conſent upon fair evidence (whereof ſacred Scripture and naturall reaſon will afford ſufficient to all perſons and Courts of Parliament) to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof.</p>
            <p>And for your owne due, none can deny, but as you are Head of all Civill powers, within your owne do mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; ſo the execution of all Civill Lawes (whereof your power is the life) for the preſervation of your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156944:13"/>in all Civill reſpects, belongeth unto you: therefore keep it to your ſelfe, and for that uſe onely, and give it not into the hands of any Eccleſiaſticall perſons, for Chriſt never called for the uſe of it, to cut off men for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake, but for incivility, and for that ſame purpoſe God did ordain it, <hi>Rom</hi> 9. And onely in this reſpect are Kings and Queenes held truely to be nurſing Fathers and Mothers, to the Church of Chriſt, for in ſo doing they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the innocent, relieve the oppreſſed, and preſerve the meek, from unreaſonable and <hi>Cain</hi>-like men of the world, and hatch up the people in generall, by main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining equity between man and man, out of which Chriſt calleth his choſen, ſuch as are appointed for the worſhip and ſpeciall ſervice of the Trinity.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe for your owne due, none can deny, ſince God hath put an end to the Jewiſh and nationall Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall ſtate; but that the uſe of all meanes ſet apart for Eccleſiaſticall uſes of right belongeth to none but perſons in Civill ſtate, of Government, the lands and Tenths ſet apart for holy perſons and holy uſes are with the holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> the holy places, holy times, and all externall holineſſe ended in Chriſt; now the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven is within, it hath not relation to the matters of this World, <hi>Iohn</hi> 18.36. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. But the devil remembreth how to coozen and cheat mankinde of old, make men beleeve they ſhall be as Gods, and the while bring them to be the greateſt ſlaves to himſelfe: let me ſpeak freely though I hang for mine uprightneſſe, ſo hath he ſince Chriſt to deceive the whole earth, even all Civil Government, ſet a company of deceivers, to lift up the Kings of the earth above their owne Element, into Chriſts ſeat: and to draw them to ſupport ſuch as are lifted up into it, and the while coozen the Kings of the earth of the greateſt part of their temporall revenues, and were it not that Princes came out of the loines of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156944:13"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and are moſt beſet with witches and delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, it were impoſſible to be thought that they ſhould be ſo handled, to be perſwaded that God ſhould put an end to a naturall generation, and raiſe an artificiall one in their ſtead, and that out of a contrary Nation, which ſhould carry five times a greater revenue of the earth than the former; conſidering how largely Chriſt and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples declared themſelves in this caſe, in the laſt recited Scriptures, and alſo in the paſſage of Tribute money, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.19, 20, 21. Once let that old devilliſh ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed opinion and proverbe be buried, I mean no Biſhop no King, it is but a deluſion and meer dreame, for what ſhall more oblige Subjects than when they have all the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that conſcience and naturall reaſon can afford them? and were it no more for fear of penalty in tranſgreſſing ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Lawes than for wounding Conſcience; what would not be done in theſe dayes? I appeal to your owne and the generall experimentall knowledge, and what pleaſure hath God in ſuch formality? Be no longer thus gulled of what is your owne, and that in a deviliſh way, to the confuſion of your owne Kingdom; for every one ſhall be ſaved or damned by his owne beleeving or unbeleeving, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.16. Not every one that ſaith Lord, Lord, ſhall enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of Heaven, &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.21. Without faith it is impoſſible for any man to pleaſe God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. For whatſoever is not of faith is ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. And ſince faith is the gift of God, not of: you, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Iames</hi> 1.17. Take to your ſelfe what is your owne, and apply and imploy both your ſword and maintenance to and in the matters of your owne Element, defending the innocent and civill, and releeving the poor and oppreſſed, then Chriſt ſhall bear rule in his owne, and amongſt his owne, and you ſhall be maſter of your owne: theſe things are eaſie to be accompliſhed by Parliament, how can any of any Religion which conceive themſelves
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156944:14"/>to be of God, be againſt the caſting off of the tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call though golden bonds of conſcience, and ſetting that at liberty they need not fear ſinking, <hi>A ts</hi> 5.39. That which is not of God ſhall have a time to be rooted up, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.13. And double and double the Lawes and execution of them in all caſes of civility, and what can your Majeſty aske that will not be yours.</p>
            <p>And let the bleſſed Trinity in their owne cauſe in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Conſcience, uſe their owne ſword which is ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per than yours, <hi>Heb.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.12. Let the light be free, not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and confined by the eyes of men, ſupport none that adde to it or detract from it, neither cut off any with your ſword which are enemies to it; but in caſes of intolerable incivility; for perſecutors may be converted, if they be not intrade and cuſtome of murdering: but if ſo, let no <hi>Caines</hi> raging on the earth live within your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; neither favour that poſterity of his who exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe his ſpirit according to, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.12.</p>
            <p>So I leave all paſſages to your royall conſideration, and commit my ſelfe in the manifeſtation of realty and faithfulneſſe in the ſervice of God, my King, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, to your Majeſties ſword of Juſtice and due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
